<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Vanshika Srivastava</title>
        <link>undefined</link>
        <description>Your blog description</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 14:56:59 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <image>
            <title>Vanshika Srivastava</title>
            <url>undefined/favicon.ico</url>
            <link>undefined</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>All rights reserved 2024</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Brief Understanding to Ethereum Scaling and ‘Optimistic’ Rollups]]></title>
            <link>undefined/articles/deep-learning-to-enhance-video-games</link>
            <guid>undefined/articles/deep-learning-to-enhance-video-games</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Team Layer1 or Layer2, you decide in the end of this blog!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images.mirror-media.xyz/publication-images/hPVXzz6ndcgvZb6NWWeyj.png?height=1000&amp;width=2000" alt="upscaled"/></p>
<h3>Introduction</h3>
<p>For the longest time, we have been fighting around Blockchain Trilemma of Decentralization, Security and Scalability. Ethereum no doubt is extremely popular in industry and is the base blockchain. Various L2s operate over Ethereum, allowing the transactions on L2 to ultimately be as secure as L1 transaction. But the question arises, why did we need L2s at first place ?
Ethereum which is L1 can roughly process less than 20 TPS, now when this demand is high, the network becomes congested, gas fees are sky-rocketing and users HATE, HATE, HATE paying such high gas fees.</p>
<p><img src="https://cdn.geeksandgamers.com/wp-content/uploads/hm_bbpui/295244/0qii5i869k4tcd75aj7yreju9edenls8.jpg" alt="upscaled"/></p>
<p>Let’s say I give you a different layer which sits on top of your Layer1 Ethereum, we are going to use this new layer for scaling the transactions without hurting the sentiments of decentralisation and security and reducing the gas fees cost. That’s L2 for you.</p>
<h2>Let’s see how ‘Rollups’ work in scaling ethereum :</h2>
<p><img src="" alt="upscaled"/></p>
<p>In the above flow, you can easily see that there are multiple transactions ‘bundled’ in ‘roll-up’. Rolled up transactions get executed on off chain which reduce is overall computation time, speed and cost and making it more easy for dApps to submit the ‘secured’ transaction data, also known as calldata on L1 finally.</p>
<p>There are two different types of Rollups -</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Optimistic Rollups</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>ZK-Proof Rollups</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>We will just discuss Optimistic Rollups in this blog. Optimistic Rollups increases the throughput of Ethereum’s Base Layer by reducing computation on-chain (or onchain).</p>
<p>Now, you must be thinking if transaction is computed offchain, how does one verify the transaction data submitted by L2 to L1 ? Your answer is Fraud Proof. As the term suggests, fraud proofs are nothing but allow verification of transactions. The way Optimistic Rollups work is by being ‘OPTIMISTIC’ because they assume that transactions are valid and there is no proof of validity which goes on-chain.</p>
<p>Let me simplify the process of using a Fraud Proof mechanism. Let’s say that 100 students are giving examination and I have prepared an aggregated score card for all the scores - bundled in a rollup sheet. Now, I would like to take help of a committee to re-verify the performance for publish purpose. The committee has a timeline of a week which you can refer as ‘challenge-period’. The committee will consider my set of results to be valid but at the same time if they suspect a score which looks ‘fraudulent’ they can challenge me, and run a proof against it to check if there are actual discrepancies or not. If my decision remains unchallenged, it passes for final publish and is accepted ‘truthful’.</p>
<h2>My takeaways from Optimistic Rollups :</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Transaction data from the rollups is stored on L1 itself. Sequencers are mostly centralised as of now, although Optimism Foundation is working on decentralised sequencer which would help the economical as well as governance mechanism within the ecosystem.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Fraud proving mechanism is helpful to chart out the finalities with ‘honesty’ and secures the chain.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Optimistic rollups are very compatible with Solidity and other EVM chains which is really helpful to smart contract developers to use the existing contracts and map them to rollups or create new dApps.</p>
</li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>vanshikasrivastava.business@gmail.com (Vanshika Srivastava)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Breaking into Tech from a non-technical background 💪]]></title>
            <link>undefined/articles/how-did-I-ended-up-in-Tech</link>
            <guid>undefined/articles/how-did-I-ended-up-in-Tech</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Get to know how I began my journey!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>The first time I felt I should go in Tech :</h3>
<p>If you ask me when did I get interested or felt like getting involved in tech, I wouldn&#x27;t have a precise answer to that.
Tech and development came to me very naturally, more of like hobby.</p>
<p>I remember the days from teenage hood, when computer science was part of school syllabus, I enjoyed helping my mates when we would build simple websites on HTML.(I know that HTML is not a programming language, pls don&#x27;t start a comment thread over that haha). All I wanted to do was explore.</p>
<blockquote>
<h3>The bottom line of stepping in Tech :</h3>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><em>I have always said that the most important part of being in Tech is that you constantly explore, learn, apply and again learn.</em> This is a never ending cycle.
The more you know, the less it is - technology will change, always and faster than you think.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3>The first time I wrote &quot;hello world&quot; :</h3>
<p>I began six years ago, the resources were limited, it took time to figure out a lot of things if you are self taught. I grew up between smartphones being just launched and facebook was still a thing.</p>
<pre><code>`My first &quot;hello world&quot; was in Python.`
</code></pre>
<p>YES, thats my first programming language and I believe I am not the only one who did this. I used to borrow books from library on Python and learn things. It was a tedious process and no doubt it paid off. Overtime, I learnt Java, MySQL and database handling with python.</p>
<h3>Coding was not a necessity but a choice :</h3>
<p>Since I began to learn things, one thing I understood about myself was - I cannot repeat the same set of tasks everyday. This meant, that even though I loved coding, I would still hop off to graphic designing and poetry (hidden talent you may call) to get some mind off from coding.
I loved communicating with people and being very honest - loved extra co-curriculars.</p>
<p>Talking about my education, in my intermediate I chose the stream which people were quite disappointed about.</p>
<p>Any guesses ?</p>
<p>I took Commerce. I felt I had strong desires to learn how business and management works but my love for IT didn&#x27;t end with this choice. Engineering was something that would have never worked out for me. I knew that, the quench of this expanding horizons in tech wouldn&#x27;t come by my degree and therefore it&#x27;s not necessary to go with a conventional choice of subject.</p>
<p>The best or strongest combination I built over years was mix of management and tech. People went from doing engineering and then taking MBA. This thing taught me a lot.</p>
<p><code>Skills + Knowledge &gt; Degree</code></p>
<h3>Some educational history :</h3>
<p>I completed my 12th in 2020, yup the first set of batch who passed during covid and couldn&#x27;t appear for two of my board exams. Out of which, one was Information Practices subject.
In both my board exams- I have always been below 90%, my college is second tier, and I am doing course in business management field.</p>
<h3>Open Source changed my life :</h3>
<p>I can&#x27;t express the importance of Time when covid struck. A lot of people lost opportunities - and I took that period as an opportunity. I jumped in Open Source. I started learning and building in Public. I overcame the fear of speaking in public when there is no script and have to mention Twitter. This twitter community has given me so much.</p>
<p>Open Source is one thing where your background will not matter as long as you know how to use Version Control and have control over one or more than one language.</p>
<p>EVERY SINGLE CONTRIBUTION COUNTS.</p>
<h3>My first stepping stone towards an internship :</h3>
<p>I started off with making non-code contributions from last year. Parallelly, I explored DevOps and learnt things around Kubernetes and Microservices. My first contribution happened to be in <a href="https://dok.community/">Data on Kubernetes Community</a>. This community is led Bart Farrell. I wrote a blog post based on one of the video and submitted it for review and good response. This boosted my confidence. With continuous contributions within community, the next amazing thing that happened was - I ended up being one of the four foundation interns at DoK Community. Kunal Kushwaha was the program head for that cohort. We learnt alot from collaborations, events and ofcourse about K8s.</p>
<p>I am keeping the rest of the experiences for next time but
one thing I do want to mention out is :</p>
<pre><code>There is no roadmap for breaking in tech.
You can&#x27;t follow someone&#x27;s exact path but
what you can do is always reach out to community
and collect as much knowledge as you can.
</code></pre>
<p>The objective of doing something related to tech should be more on the side of learning and giving something valuable to people</p>
<hr/>
<p>In the end, I have just gratitude for the amazing community that has supported and motivated me to do better things - <strong>consistently</strong> .</p>
<p><em>Do let me know in comments if this blog helped you to get a clarity of thoughts or anything else that you would like to share :)</em></p>
<p>Until next time😃</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>vanshikasrivastava.business@gmail.com (Vanshika Srivastava)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>